Finding Aid for Johnston Family Papers 1822-1936
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Johnston Family Papers 1822-1936
Johnston family.
Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, family. Correspondence, photographs, and other papers of John Johnston, fur trader, son John McDouall Johnston, Indian interpreter for Henry R. Schoolcraft, and other family members; including letters containing impressions of Indian life and historical materials concerning Indian grammar and folklore, and the history of the Sault Ste. Marie, Michigan, region. Includes letter, Jan. 24, 1822, from John Johnston to Lewis Cass discussing Indian affairs.
85221 Aa 2
0.75 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was donated by David Harlow (donor no. 6448 ) in 1980. Mr. Harlow had found the materials in the remains of an old house on Drummond Island, Michigan.
The collection is open for research.
John Johnston was among the earliest permanent English-speaking settlers of Sault Ste. Marie. Born at Craige in Antrim county (in northern Ireland) in 1762, Johnston left his home and family in 1790 to come to Canada. He remained here until 1793 when he crossed over to Sault Ste. Marie to establish himself in the fur trade near the headwaters of the St. Mary's Falls.
Johnston would make his home here for the next thirty-five years until his death in 1828. His business depended upon a close relationship with the Indians of the regions, most notably the Objibwa or Chippewas. Johnston eventually married "Susan" (d. 1843), the daughter of one of their chiefs, named Waubojeeg. Together, they would have eight children - four boys and four girls. The children were Louis (1793-1825); George (1796-1861); Jane (1800-1842), who married Henry R. Schoolcraft, the noted Indian scholar and government Superintendent of Indian Affairs; Eliza (1802-1885); Charlotte (1806-1871); William (b. 1811); Anna Maria (b. 1814); and John McDouall (1816-1895), who worked for Schoolcraft among the Indians, and later became a U.S. Indian Commissioner.
The Johnston family papers contains approximately seven inches of correspondence, writings, clippings, and photographs. The collection falls into three series: Johnston family papers, Collected historical and Indian materials, and Photographs.
Subjects:
Cass, Lewis, 1782-1866.; Frontier and pioneer life--Michigan--Sault Sainte Marie.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Johnston family.; Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Schoolcraft, Henry Rowe, 1793-1864.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Boats.; Camping.; Children.; Churches.; De Tour Village (Mich.); Drummond Island (Mich.); Dwellings.; Indians of North America--Michigan.; Johnston, George, 1796-1861.; Johnston, John, 1762-1828.; Johnston, John McDouall, 1816-1895.; Neebish Island (Mich.); Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Schoolcraft, Jane Johnston, 1800-1842.; Sleds and sleighs.; Upper Peninsula (Mich.)
Contributors:
Johnston, John, 1762-1828.; Johnston, John McDouall, 1816-1895.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.; Tintypes.
- Johnston family file 1822-1936
  - Genealogical and biographical material (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous notes and fragments (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous 1etters, notes, and writings 1894-1956 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - John Johnston (1762-1828)
    - Fragments from journal 1826 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence 1822-1828 (original and copies of l letters in newspaper) (Box 1)
    - Copy of gravestone inscription (Box 1)
  - John McDouall Johnston (1816-1895), son of John Johnston
    - Papers 1843, 1853, 1858-1893 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
    - Biographical materials and miscellaneous writings (Box 1)
  - Anna Maria "Mollie" Johnston (1844-1928), daughter of John M. Johnston
    - Correspondence 1923-1928 and death certificate (Box 1)
    - Recollections of Johnston House 1910 or 1911 (Box 1)
  - Charlotte Jane Johnston (1847-1919), daughter of John M. Johnston
    - Papers circa 1874-1919 including letter, poetry, newspaper obituary, and programs of music recitals (Box 1)
  - James Lawrence Johnston (1851-), son of John M. Johnston
    - Letter from sister "Mollie" 1913 (Box 1)
  - William Meddaugh Johnston (1858-), son of John M. Johnston
    - Correspondence 1910-1931 and notebook 1920s (Box 1)
- Photographs 1896-1925
  - Address book undated (Box 1)
  - Papers concerning Rev. Daniel Coe and other early missionaries to the Sault region (Box 1)
  - Guest Book for Ononegwud Lodge 1896-1898 (Box 1)
  - Indian materials
    - Genealogical table of Leila Lufkins, Chippewa Indian (Box 1)
    - Vocabulary, miscellaneous song and verse (Box 1)
    - The story of Manaboyha undated (Box 1)
    - Indian land certificate and other legal agreements 1865 undated, 1925 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper clippings re. early "500"/Indian history (Box 1)
  - Schoolcraft, Henry R., newspaper article (1902) on "Wabojeeg, Great Sioux Chief," reprinted from book Oneota (1844) (Box 1)
  - Brochures for Sault Ste. Marie activities (Box 1)
- Photographs
  - Portraits
    - Allen family (Box 1)
    - Anthony, Eliza, family (Box 1)
    - Anthony, Retta (Box 1)
    - Dore family (Box 1)
    - Douglas, Ella Mabel (Box 1)
    - Healy, Hill, Hubbard families (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Eliza Jane (Box 1)
    - Johnston, George, and Mary Rice Johnston (Box 1)
  - Portraits (cont.)
    - Johnston, Henry, family (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Howard and Mollie, family (Box 1)
    - Johnston, John, family (Box 1)
    - Johnston, John M., and Justine Piguette Johnston (Box 1)
    - Johnston, Spencer, family (Box 1)
    - Johnston; William, family (Box 1)
    - McMurray, James, and Charlotte Johnston McMurray family (Box 1)
    - Schoolcraft, Jane Johnston, family (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous individuals
      - Identified (Box 1)
      - Unidentified female (Box 1)
      - Unidentified male (Box 1)
    - Tintypes (Box 1)
  - Other photos
    - Homes (Neebish, Drummond, etc.) (Box 1)
    - Outdoor activities (including camping, boating, sleighing) (Box 1)
    - Travel (Winnipeg and Victoria, B.C.) (Box 1)
    - Views (Drummond, De Tour, Neebish, Sault Ste. Marie) (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)